[{"question":"In plants, growth is:","a":"a) Restricted to certain regions or structure","b":"(b) Irreversible","c":"(c) Change in size","d":"(d) All of the above","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Growth is primarily Affected Factors which are: by  two climatic","a":"(a) Light and temperature","b":"(B) Temperature and relative humidity","c":"(c) Light and wind","d":"(c) Rainfall and temperature","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following instrument can be used to record plant growth by seconds?","a":"(a) Arc auxanometer","b":"(b) Arc indicator","c":"(c) Space marker disc","d":"(d) Crescograph","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Plant growth is ultimately regulated by:","a":"(a) Environmental cues","b":"(b) Hormones","c":"(c) Signal transduction pathways","d":"c) The plant's genome","hint":"Though the  environment influences  development. final regulation is at the  genomic level.","correct":"d"},{"question":"The process in which mature differentiated  cells reverse to meristematic activity to form callus is called:","a":"(a) Cytodifferentiation","b":"(b) redifferentiation","c":"(c) dedifferentiation","d":"(d) differentiation","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which one of the following is primarily concerned with cell  division","a":"(a) GA3","b":"(b)  IAA","c":"c) Cytokinin","d":"(d) IBA","hint":"Cytokinins induce cell division in plants and thus influence the plant growth by controlling cell division.","correct":"c"},{"question":"The discovery of gibberellins is related with  which one of the following?","a":"(a) Blast disease of rice","b":"(b) Bakanae disease of rice","c":"(c) Early blight disease of potato","d":"c) Rust disease of wheat","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following light receptors is responsible for absorbing blue and ultraviolet light? ","a":"(a) Phytochrome P,","b":"(B) Photochrome P","c":"(c) Cryptochrome","d":"(D)Phototropin ","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"In short day plants (SDP) flowering is induced by","a":"(a) Photoperiod less than 12 hours","b":"b) Photoperiod shorter than initial value and uninterrupted long night ","c":"(c) Short photoperiod and interrupted long night","d":"(D) long night","hint":"Short-day plants flower, only if light periods are shorter than some critical length. In these plants the dark period is critical and must be continuous. If this dark period is interrupted even with a brief exposure of light, the short day plant will not flower. Strawberries, Dahlias, soyabeans and Chrysanthemums are short day plants","correct":"b"},{"question":"Most appropriate temperature for vernalization is","a":"(a) 1-6°C","b":"(b) 7°C","c":"(c) - 6 deg °C","d":"d) 0 deg ° C","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Cell elongation in internode regions of the green plants takes place due to","a":"(a) Ethylene","b":"b) Indole acetic acid","c":"(c) Cytokinin","d":"(d) Gibberellins","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"An enzyme that can stimulate germination of barley seeds is","a":"(a) Protease","b":"(b) Invertase","c":"(c) a-amylase","d":"(d) Lipase","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The natural plant hormones were first isolated from","a":"(a) Corn germ oil and human urine","b":"(b) Cotton fruits, spinach leaves and rice plants","c":"(C) Human urine and rice seedlings","d":"(d) Spinach leaves and fungus Gibberella","hint":"The first naturally occurring auxin was  isolated by Kogl and Haagen-Smit (1931)  from human urine. It was identified as  auxin-a (auxentriolic acid). Later, in 1934  Kogl, Haagen-Smit and Erxleben obtained  another auxin called auxin-b (auxenolonic  acid) from corn germ oil (extracted from  germinating corn seeds).","correct":"a"},{"question":"Maximum amount of growth in root occurs:  17.","a":"(a) in the presence of light.","b":"(b) at its apex","c":"(c) behind the apex","d":"(d) in the presence of soil.","hint":"Root meristem is sub-apical in position","correct":"c"},{"question":"Cytokinins are known to:","a":"(a) Inhibit cytoplasmic movement","b":"(b) Help in retention of chlorophyll","c":"(c) Influence water movement","d":"(d) Promote abscission layer formation","hint":")  Less chlorophyll and degeneration of proteins are the two important symptoms of senescence. Cytokinins delay these processes and, thus senescence is also delayed. This effect of cytokinin is known as Richmond-Lang effect.","correct":"b"},{"question":"Apical dominance means:","a":"(a) Suppression of growth of apical by Axillary buds. ","b":"(b) Suppression of growth of axillary buds by the presence of apical bud","c":"(c) Stimulation of growth of axillary buds by removal of apical bud ","d":"(d) Inhibition of growth of axillary buds by removal of apical bud","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Auxin inhibits the growth of:","a":"(a) Apical bud","b":"(b) Lateral axillary buds","c":"(c) Roots on stem cutting","d":"(d) Parthenocarpic development of fruits","hint":"Auxin inhibits the growth of lateral axillary Buds","correct":"b"},{"question":"The growth rate is highest  in:","a":"(a) Red light","b":"b) White light","c":"(c) Green light","d":"(d) Blue light","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Leaf movement in Mimosa pudica (Sensitive plant) due to: ","a":"a) Nerve impulsion","b":"b) Delicate leaves","c":"c) Loss of tissue","d":"d) Turgor change in leaf base","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Ageing is retarded by:","a":"(a) ABA","b":"(b) CKN","c":"(c) GA","d":"(d) C₂H4","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Auxin causes cells to absorb water from hypertonic media because","a":"(a) it lowers transpiration rate","b":"(b) it increases rate of cellular respiration causing more production of ATP molecules  thus facilitating active water absorption.","c":"(c) it increases solute potential of the cells.","d":"(d) it increase rate of transpiration.","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The hormone reducing transpiration rate by inducing stomatal closure is: ","a":"(a) ABA","b":"b) Ethylene","c":"(c) Cytokinin","d":"d) Auxin","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Richmond-Lang effect is concerned with:","a":"(a) delay in senescence","b":"(b) breaking dormancy","c":"(c) suppression of apical dominance","d":"(d) cell elongation","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which is employed for artificial ripening of banana fruits?","a":"(a) Auxin","b":"b) Coumarin","c":"c) Ethylene","d":"(d) Cytokinin","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The movement of auxin is largely:","a":"(a) Both acropetal and basipetal","b":"(b) Basipetal","c":"c) Centripetal","d":"(d) Acropetal","hint":"The movement of auxin is polar and in stem it takes place in a basipetal direction, whereas in the roots it is in an acropetal direction","correct":"a"},{"question":"I.A.A. mainly inhibits growth of","a":"(a) Root","b":"(b) Leaf","c":"c) Shoot","d":"(d) Generally whole plant","hint":"L.A.A. mainly inhibits growth of root.","correct":"a"},{"question":"The names of many organisms are associated  with classical studies in some areas of biology. Which of the following does not show such matching","a":"(a) Pea-Laws of heredity","b":"b) Acetabularia-Relationship Between Nucleus and cytoplasm","c":"(c) E. coli-Genetic engineering","d":"(d) Barley seeds- Role of phytochrome","hint":"Barley seeds are associated with o-amylase bioassay of gibberellins.","correct":"d"},{"question":"The plants bend towards light because:","a":"(a) the stem likes sunlight","b":"(b) the roots send the message to the stem to do so","c":"(c) due to secretion of growth promoting substances at the tip.","d":"(d) the food material is translocated From Leaves to stem causing bending","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Phytotron is device for","a":"(a) induction of mutations","b":"(b) measuring wind velocity","c":"(C) measuring electron flow","d":"d) growing plants under controlled conditions","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the following hormones can replace vernalisation ","a":"(a) Ethylene","b":"(b) Gibberellins","c":"(c) Cytokinins","d":"d) Auxins","hint":"Gibberellin overcomes vernalisation requirement (low temperature) for flowering.","correct":"b"},{"question":"When a dark period in SDP is interrupted by a  brief exposure of light, the plant:","a":"(a) Will not flower at all","b":"(b) Flowers immediatly","c":"(c) Gives more flowers","d":"(d) Turns into LDP","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Stem elongation is affected by:","a":"a) Gibberellin and florigen","b":"(b) Auxin and gibberellin","c":"(c) Florigen and kinin","d":"d) Kinin and auxin","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Growth is primarily affected by  two climatic factors which are","a":"(a) Light and temperature","b":"(b) Temperature and relative humidity","c":"(c) Light and wind","d":"d) Rainfall and temperature","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Parthenocarpic tomato fruits can be Produced By:","a":"a) Raising the plants from vernalised seeds","b":"(b) Treating the plants with Phenomena Acetate","c":"(c) Removing androecium of flowers before pollen grains are released","d":"(d) Treating the plants with low concentrations  of gibberellic acid and auxins.","hint":") Parthenocarpic tomato fruits can be produced by treating the plants with low  concentrations of gibberellic acid and","correct":"d"},{"question":"Induction of rooting in stem cutting by auxin  treatment would be beneficial in which of the  following? ","a":"(a) Marchantia","b":"(b) Wheat","c":"(c) Cuscuta","d":"(d) Bougainvillea","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The growth of the plant body takes place by:","a":"(a) Lateral meristems","b":"(b) Apical meristems","c":"(c) Both apical and lateral meristems","d":"d) None of the above","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"What will be the effect on phytochrome in Plant subjected to continuous red light?","a":"(a) Level of phytochrome decreases","b":"b) Phytochrome is destroyed","c":"(c) Phytochrome synthesis increases","d":"(d) Destruction and synthesis of phytochrome remain in equilibrium","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which one of the following is a long day plant?","a":"(a) Bajra","b":"(b) Soyabean","c":"(c) Tobacco","d":"(d) Wheat","hint":"Long-day plants usually flower in the spring or early summer; they flower only if the light periods are longer than a critical length, which is usually 9-16 hours. For example, wheat plants flower only when light periods exceed fourteen hours.","correct":"d"},{"question":"Seedless fruits can be obtained by treating the unpollinated ovaries with","a":"(a) Colchicine","b":"(b) Sucrose solution","c":"(c) Hormones","d":"(d) Pure lanolin","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following test will you perform to demonstrate the presence of gibberellin?","a":"a) Bolting of cabbage","b":"(b) Differentiation of shoots in tobacco callus culture ","c":"(c) Rapid division in carrot cells","d":"d) Elongation of Avena coleoptile","hint":"Bolting of cabbage can be induced artificially by the application of gibberellin under conditions that would normally maintain the rossette form.","correct":"a"},{"question":"","a":"","b":"","c":"","d":"","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"","a":"","b":"","c":"","d":"","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"","a":"","b":"","c":"","d":"","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"","a":"","b":"","c":"","d":"","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"","a":"","b":"","c":"","d":"","hint":"","correct":"c"}]